<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oleg Sobchuk on Oleg Sobchuk: Macroevolution of the Arts</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Oleg Sobchuk on Oleg Sobchuk: Macroevolution of the Arts</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2024, Oleg Sobchuk.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ndash; PDF, &amp;ndash; data and code&#xA;Preprints Lee H, Anglada-Tort M, Sobchuk O, van Rijn P, Schönwiesner M, Tchernichovski O, Park M, Jacoby N Global music discoveries reveal cultural shifts during the war in Ukraine, in review Dubourg E, Thouzeau V, et al. The cognitive foundations of fictional stories, in review, Psychology Inquiry Books Sobchuk O (forthcoming) Stories Evolve: A Theory of Historical Change for Computational Humanities. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/research.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/research.html</guid>
      <description>Are modern movies more complex than old ones? Are modern movies better than old ones? Is Lawrence of Arabia superior to Dune? One might say: fighting over tastes is tasteless. True. But this question isn&amp;rsquo;t purely about taste. If old movies are so good, why do we keep watching new ones? This question has always bothered me, and so Peeter Tinits and I decided to operationalize it. Could it be that modern movies are more technologically superior, similarly to how modern airplanes are more superior to old ones?</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
