<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oleg Sobchuk on Oleg Sobchuk: Macroevolution of the Arts</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Oleg Sobchuk on Oleg Sobchuk: Macroevolution of the Arts</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2024, Oleg Sobchuk.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ndash; PDF, &amp;ndash; data and code&#xA;Unpublished (yet) Sobchuk O, Youngblood M, Morin O. First-mover advantage in music, in review, EPJ Data Science Dubourg E, Thouzeau V, et al. The cognitive foundations of fictional stories, in review, Psychology Review Books Sobchuk O (forthcoming) Stories Evolve: A Theory of Historical Change for Computational Humanities. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&#xA;Sobchuk O (2018) Charting Artistic Evolution: An Essay in Theory. Tartu: University of Tartu Press Papers Sobchuk, O, Šeļa, A (2024).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/research.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/research.html</guid>
      <description>Are modern movies more complex than old ones? Are modern movies better than old ones? Is Lawrence of Arabia superior to Dune? One might say: fighting over tastes is tasteless. True. But this question isn&amp;rsquo;t purely about taste. If old movies are so good, why do we keep watching new ones? This question has always bothered me, and so Peeter Tinits and I decided to operationalize it. Could it be that modern movies are more technologically superior, similarly to how modern airplanes are more superior to old ones?</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
